<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A looking-glasse for Levellers: held out in a sermon, preached at St. Peters Pauls-Wharfe, upon Sunday in the after-noone, Sept. 24. 1648. / By Paul Knell, Master in Arts, of Clare-Hall in Cambridge. Sometime chaplain to a regiment of curasiers in His Majesties Army.</title>
            <author>Knell, Paul, 1615?-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87809</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K683</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E465_30</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204195</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863866</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863866</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116082</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87809)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116082)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 74:E465[30])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A looking-glasse for Levellers: held out in a sermon, preached at St. Peters Pauls-Wharfe, upon Sunday in the after-noone, Sept. 24. 1648. / By Paul Knell, Master in Arts, of Clare-Hall in Cambridge. Sometime chaplain to a regiment of curasiers in His Majesties Army.</title>
                  <author>Knell, Paul, 1615?-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October] 4th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Levellers --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116082:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> LOOKING-GLASSE FOR LEVELLERS: <hi>Held out in a SERMON,</hi> Preached at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peters Pauls-Wharfe,</hi> upon Sunday in the After-noone, <hi>Sept.</hi> 24. 1648.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> PAUL KNELL, Maſter in Arts, of <hi>Clare-Hall</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi> Sometime Chaplain to a Regiment of Curaſiers in <hi>His Majeſties Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LUKE 20.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And the chief Prieſts and Scribes the ſame houre ſought to lay hands on him (but they feared the people) for they perceived that he had ſpoken this parable againſt them.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed in the Year, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116082:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> LOOKING-GLASSE For LEVELLERS, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. LUKE 20. ver. 14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But when the Husbandmen ſaw him, they reaſoned among themſelves, ſaying, This is the Heire, come let us kill him, that the Inheritance may be ours.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt particle is diſcretive, and ſevereth the Text from the fore-going Verſes, wherein our Saviour holdeth forth, as it were, a Dark-Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne to the chief Prieſts, That <hi>ſeeing they might ſee, and not perceive, and that hearing they might heare, and yet not underſtand.</hi> Or rather he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them their faces in a Glaſſe, wherein they might ſee plainly what manner of men they were. The <hi>Looking-glaſſe</hi> is this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parable of the <hi>Vineyard,</hi> wherein he inſiſteth chiefly on three things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> he ſheweth the deſcent and pedegree of the Prieſthood, <hi>A certain man planted a Vineyard, and let it forth to Huſband-men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> he upbraideth the ingratitude of theſe Husband-men in abuſing their Land-lords ſervants, <hi>they beat them, they intreated them ſhamefully, they wounded them, they killed them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> he threatneth a puniſhment for their ingratitude,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116082:3"/>which is no leſſe then a re-enter, <hi>the Lord ſhall deſtroy theſe Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band-men, and ſhall give the Vineyard to others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But more punctually to ſurvey and view this parable. By this <hi>certain man,</hi> the Planter of this <hi>Vineyard,</hi> we are to underſtand the <hi>worlds Creator,</hi> God himſelf. By the <hi>Vineyard,</hi> we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>his Church,</hi> confined for a long time to <hi>Judea, Iſa.</hi> 5.7. By the <hi>Huſband-men,</hi> to whom the Vineyard was let out, we are to underſtand the <hi>chief Prieſts,</hi> who by their doctrine and example were, as it were, to prune and dreſſe Gods Vineyard, that ſo it might be fruitfull in good works. By the <hi>Servants</hi> ſent to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand ſome of the fruit of this Vineyard, we are to underſtand the inſpired Prophets, who were ſent by God to call the chief Prieſts to repentance, to bring forth fruits worthy of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life. <hi>Trium autem mentio fit, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith <hi>Aretius,</hi> God is ſaid to have ſent ſeverally three Servants to the Husbandmen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>three</hi> is a perfect number, and is therefore uſed to ſhew Gods unceſſant deſire of their Converſion. Unceſſant, I ſay, it was, for though it knew a little intermiſſion, yet it knew no ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, though the word of the Lord were pretious in the daies of <hi>Eli,</hi> yet even then God raiſed up <hi>Samuel</hi> to reprove the lewdneſſe of the Prieſts, there was no time, there was no place but the Jewiſh Prieſts had Prophets ſent among them. Before their Captivity in <hi>Babylon,</hi> they had <hi>Iſaiah; Jeremy, Amos, Micah, Zephany,</hi> and others. In time of their Captivity, they had <hi>Ezekiel</hi> and <hi>Daniel.</hi> After their Captivity, they had <hi>Haggai, Zechary, Malachy.</hi> And the laſt was not the leaſt, for <hi>among thoſe that were borne of Women, there was not a greater Prophet then John the Baptiſt.</hi> But what entertainment found theſe Servants amongſt their Maſters Tenants? why juſt ſuch as we that will not Preach <hi>treaſon</hi> meet with in theſe days, juſt ſuch as the Meſſengers of <hi>truth</hi> have alway found, <hi>convitia, verba, vulnera,</hi> as <hi>Stella</hi> ſpeaketh, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilings, blowes, wounds; nay, very death it ſelfe. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was ſawn aſunder, <hi>Jeremy</hi> and <hi>Zechary</hi> were ſtoned, <hi>Amos</hi> had his braines beaten out with a Club, <hi>Micah</hi> was thrown down head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long from a rock; and all the reſt did the Jewes either kill, or at leaſt hunt after them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as S. <hi>Steven</hi> asked them, <hi>which of the Prophets did not their Fathers perſecute? Act.</hi> 7. yet ſee the never-wearied goodneſſe of Almighty God, though
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116082:3"/>the chief Prieſts had <hi>killed his Prophets,</hi> and had <hi>ſtoned thoſe that were ſent unto them,</hi> yet he did ſo long to doe them good, that <hi>nullum non movebit lapidem,</hi> he will leave no ſtone unrolled, no not the corner-ſtone, he had but one boſome-Son, and he ſendeth him to them for his rent, preſuming that for ſhame they would not ſend him away empty, <hi>They wil reverence</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>their young Land-lord</hi> when they ſee him, <hi>But when the Huſband-men ſaw him, they reaſoned among themſelves, ſaying, this is the Heire, come let us kill him, that the inheritance may be ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Text, ye ſee, is a conſpiracy againſt Chriſt, wherein we meet together the foure cauſes of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> here is the Efficient cauſe, or the Conſpiratours, <hi>the Huſband-men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> the Materiall cauſe, or perſon conſpired againſt, <hi>the Heire, when they ſaw him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the Formall cauſe, or manner of their conſpiracy, <hi>they reaſoned among themſelves, ſaying, come let us kill him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> and <hi>laſtly,</hi> the Finall cauſe, or end of their conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which was, that they might be Lords of the Mannour, <hi>that the inheritance may be ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the parts, of which in order briefly, and very plainly. I begin with the firſt part, the Conſpiratours, which are <hi>Coloni,</hi> the Husband-men.</p>
            <p>If the firſt man had been a good Husband, there had been no Husband-man, the Earth need have had no Mid-wife, ſhe would have brought forth of her ſelf. But <hi>Haec maledictio Adae, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi> this was a curſe entailed on <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, that for his ſake the ground it ſelfe was curſed, his barrenneſſe in obedience made the very Earth grow barren. Which may therefore ſerve to mind us ſinners of repentance, the husbandry of the hand may teach us the husbandry of the heart, even to <hi>breake up our fallow ground,</hi> and <hi>ſow in teares.</hi> But I muſt not inſiſt upon theſe Geor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicks, I muſt lead you from corporall to ſpirituall <hi>huſband-men.</hi> And theſe are the painfull Preachers of Gods word. For as the Earth muſt be plowed and harrowed by the Country-man, before ſhe will ever bring forth her increaſe: So the men of the earth muſt be directed and corrected by the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, before they will bring forth the fruits of righteouſneſſe.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116082:4"/>The Clergy, like the Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> are a kind of Plow-men. They that doe, as it were, drive the Plow, are ordinary Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; they that hold the Plow, are the reverend Biſhops; the Plow would not go ſo well, ſhould <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> be <hi>aboliſhed.</hi> Let theſe Labourers therefore have their due, they are worthy of their hire. And let them likewiſe have a reſpectfull eſtimation ſet upon them.</p>
            <p>For the Courtier cannot live without the Country-man, <hi>the King himſelfe is ſerved by the Field.</hi> Neither doth <hi>man live by Bread only, but by every word of God.</hi> As then where no <hi>Huſhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> are the people <hi>ſterve:</hi> So likewiſe where no <hi>Miniſters,</hi> where no <hi>viſion</hi> is, <hi>the people periſh.</hi> Which admoniſheth Gods husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the Clergy, to be induſtrious.</p>
            <p>There is no profeſſion more laborious then that of Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who in the <hi>ſweat of their face</hi> moſt commonly <hi>eate their bread.</hi> And herein they are a patterne and enſample unto us, who indeed ſhould <hi>labour more abundantly then they all,</hi> becauſe they labour but to ſuſtaine mens bodies, we to feed their ſoules. We muſt therefore: <hi>abound alwaies in the worke of the Lord, we muſt Preach the word,</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> charged <hi>Timothy, not ſlothfully, but painfully,</hi> we muſt labour in the Goſpel, we muſt be inſtant, and eager, and earneſt in our preaching, <hi>in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon,</hi> in time of peace, in time of warre, we muſt <hi>reprove,</hi> we muſt <hi>rebuke,</hi> we we muſt <hi>exhort,</hi> with <hi>all long ſuffering</hi> and <hi>doctrine,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh.</p>
            <p>And as we muſt be fervent, ſo we muſt be perſeverant in our office, having put our hand to Gods plow, we muſt reſolve not to look back. <hi>We muſt not,</hi> with <hi>Demas, forſake</hi> our function, and <hi>embrace the world;</hi> nor muſt we ceaſe to exerciſe it, till we juſt put off this tabernacle though there be never ſo great danger in the exerciſing of it, though there be never ſo many wicked war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants out againſt us, Husband-men will not give over plowing for a ſhowre of raine, nor muſt we give over Preaching becauſe of perſecution, though we are never ſo ſuperannuated, though we are ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> the aged, or though ſo feeble, that, with St. <hi>John,</hi> we muſt be carried to the Pulpit. Neither muſt we lord it over Gods heritage, like Presbyterian Paſtors, or like theſe chiefe Prieſts, who that they may be Lords of the Lords Vineyard, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116082:4"/>to murder the right Lord of it, the Conſpirators, our Text telleth us, were <hi>Coloni,</hi> the <hi>Huſband-men.</hi> And ſo likewiſe <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilate</hi> told our Saviour, <hi>Thine owne Nation, and the chiefe Prieſts have delivered thee unto me, Joh.</hi> 18.35. What prodigious unthankfull miſcreants were theſe! there can be no Epithet bad enough for ſuch Traytours. For they that taught the people, taught they not themſelves? They that were dreſſers of the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, durſt they conſpire againſt the owner of it? durſt men of the Temple venture upon the worſt of treaſons? well, we ſee by this the truth of that old axiome, <hi>Corruptio optimi eſt peſſima,</hi> the beſt wine maketh the ſharpeſt vineger; if Clergy-men once turn Traytours, they are incarnate Devils. So our Saviour ſtiled the traytour <hi>Judas,</hi> and thus likewiſe all <hi>Synod-traytours</hi> may be ſtiled. And ſo I paſſe from the firſt part of the Text, the Conſpirators, the <hi>Huſband-men,</hi> to the ſecond, the perſon againſt whom they conſpired, which was the <hi>Heire, when the Huſband-men ſaw him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Heire.</hi> The wiſe God of peace and order, will not have every man be his owne carver, for the beſt weapon would then be the beſt evidence, as <hi>Levellers</hi> would fain have it; the ſtrongeſt arm would be the ſureſt title. But as he hath ordained a ſucceſſion of men, ſo of Eſtates, their Children muſt be their Heires, they muſt leave their ſubſtance to their Babes, <hi>Dominio non fundatur in gratia,</hi> they that call themſelves <hi>babes of grace,</hi> all things are not theirs, had not <hi>Jacob</hi> ſupplanted <hi>Eſau,</hi> this graceleſſe one had been <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac's</hi> Heire. For the inheritance was alway challenged by the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Son; and therefore this title of <hi>Heire,</hi> muſt needs be due to Chriſt, who was the firſt begotten of his Heavenly Father, the firſt-borne of his Earthly Mother, the firſt-borne of every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the firſt-borne among many Brethren, by right of primoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture he was the Heir, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heir of all things,</hi> Heb. 1.2. <hi>The earth is the Lords, and all that therein is, the compaſſe of the world, and they that dwell therein,</hi> Pſal. 24.1. And he that is owner of all things, maketh his eldeſt Son a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of them, he promiſeth to give him <hi>the heathen for his inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and the uttermoſt parts of the earth for his poſſeſſion,</hi> Pſal. 2.8.</p>
            <p>The Devill, I know, made his brags once, that <hi>he was Heire of the world,</hi> when he ſhewed our Saviour all <hi>the Kingdomes of it,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:116082:5"/>and told him, <hi>they were his.</hi> But as he was a <hi>murderer,</hi> ſo he was <hi>a lyar from the beginning.</hi> It is true that <hi>Abraham</hi> had a promiſe, that <hi>he ſhould be Heire of the World,</hi> as the Apoſtle teſtifyeth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13. But though to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed there were ſuch a promiſe made, yet Chriſt, for all this, was ſtill to be the Heire, it is the ſame Apoſtles obſervation, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. <hi>He ſaith not to ſeeds, as of many, but to thy ſeed, as of one, which is Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here we muſt not be miſtaken, for though our Saviour be ſtiled <hi>the Heire,</hi> yet we muſt know that his inheritance is no tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, but a ſpirituall inheritance, his Kingdome, his Church, his heritage is not of this world. And as we Chriſtians are not of it, ſo our inheritance properly is not in it, we are <hi>Heires</hi> to a <hi>better Country,</hi> that is an <hi>Heavenly,</hi> though not by <hi>nature,</hi> yet by <hi>grace,</hi> though not by <hi>birth,</hi> yet by <hi>faith</hi> we are made <hi>partabers of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of the Saints in light,</hi> we are <hi>heires of God, co heires with Chriſt,</hi> we have an <hi>inheritance incorruptible</hi> and <hi>undefiled,</hi> and <hi>that fadeth not away, reſerved in Heaven for us, where we ſhall ſee the Son of man ſitting on the right hand of God,</hi> where we ſhall ſee our <hi>pierced-Saviour,</hi> not to our <hi>terrour,</hi> but our <hi>triumph,</hi> where we ſhal ſee him not with <hi>other,</hi> but with theſe <hi>ſame eyes,</hi> the ſame nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mericall, though not the ſame mortall eyes, where we ſhall ſee that which Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſo much wiſhed to ſee, <hi>Chriſtum in carne,</hi> Chriſt in the fleſh, and that which <hi>many Prophets and Kings deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſee, and could not ſee it.</hi> They ſaw this ſight indeed a far off, which did not a little chear their hearts, <hi>Abraham rejoyced,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>to ſee my day, and he ſaw it, and was glad,</hi> John 8.56. But when <hi>Simeon</hi> ſaw him in the Temple, his eyes were ſatisfied with ſeeing, cloſe them now, <hi>Lord,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>let me die in peace, for mine eyes have ſeen thy ſalvation.</hi> And we may obſerve here by the way, that if ever we will ſee Chriſt in Heaven, we muſt firſt ſee him upon earth, for though we cannot ſee him yet, as <hi>Simeon</hi> (and theſe chief Prieſts) did, with the eyes of our body, yet we may ſee him, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did, with the perſpective of our faith, we may, &amp; we muſt ſee him thorow this glaſſe <hi>darkly,</hi> before ever we can ſee him <hi>face to face.</hi> A Chriſtian muſt not be like a Cyclop, with one eye; the ſpouſe of Chriſt, as <hi>Peraldus</hi> obſerveth, muſt have two, <hi>oculum fidei,</hi> and <hi>oculum gloriae,</hi> the eye of faith, and the eye of fruition. We muſt walk by faith, before we can walk
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116082:5"/>by ſight. We muſt, like <hi>Jacob,</hi> be firſt married to blear eyed <hi>Leak,</hi> before we can obtain beautifull <hi>Rachel;</hi> we muſt firſt ſee our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour with the tender eye of faith, before ever we can behold him with the brighter eye of glory.</p>
            <p>Now though our Saviour pronounce them <hi>bleſſed that have not ſeen, and yet have believed,</hi> and though <hi>Faith</hi> be defined by the Apoſtle, <hi>the evidence of things not ſeen;</hi> yet <hi>Segniùs irritant animos, &amp;c.</hi> as the Poet ſpeaketh, a man will give more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to his eyes, then to his ears, Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> would not go by hear-ſay, except he might ſee, he reſolved not to believe. But the chief Prieſts were ſo perverſe, that they would not believe their own eyes, for they conſpired againſt our Saviour, though they ſaw him, though they knew him, though they knew him to be the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and could ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>This is the Heire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence we may obſerve, that as there is a zeale without knowledg, ſo there is a knowledg without faith. The very Devils knew our Saviour, they knew him to be <hi>the Son of God, Mat.</hi> 3.29. <hi>Jeſus I know,</hi> ſaid the evill Spirit to thoſe Exorciſts, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.15. But their knowledge was meerly hiſtoricall, like their faith. And juſt after this manner did the chief Prieſts know Chriſt. There are indeed ſome places of Scripture that ſeem to contradict our Text, and to ſay, that the chief Prieſts knew not <hi>Jeſus</hi> to be <hi>Chriſt,</hi> knew not that he was the Heire. For Saint <hi>John</hi> ſaith plainly, that <hi>the world knew him not, Joh.</hi> 1.10. And Saint <hi>Peter</hi> upbraiding the Jewes for <hi>killing the Prince of life,</hi> uſeth theſe very words, <hi>I wot that through ignorance ye did it, as did alſo your Rulers, Act.</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <p>And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking <hi>of the wiſdome of God,</hi> which I take to be his Son, telleth us in expreſſe words, that <hi>none of the Princes of this world knew it, for had they known it, they would not have cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Lord of glory,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.8.</p>
            <p>But I anſwer, <hi>Firſt,</hi> to that of Saint <hi>John, the world knew not Chriſt,</hi> that is, the greateſt part of it, to that of Saint <hi>Paul, none of the Princes of this world knew him,</hi> that is, few of them; to that of Saint <hi>Peter, the Jewes and their Rulers ſlew him ignorantly,</hi> that is, ſome of them did ſo: thus the ordinary gloſſe would have thoſe places conſtrued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I anſwer, that the ignorance of the chief Prieſts was not <hi>purae negationis,</hi> but <hi>pravae diſpoſitionis,</hi> if they were ignorant
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116082:6"/>of Chriſt, it was becauſe they would be ignorant, as the people uſed to ſay to their Seers, <hi>ſee not,</hi> ſo theſe Seers ſeem to have ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped their eares, and ſhut their eyes, for otherwiſe they could not chuſe but acknowledge <hi>Jeſus</hi> to be the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> becauſe all the Prophecies of his comming were fulfilled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> that Prophecy, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10. pointing at the time of his Birth, <hi>the Scepter was then departed from Judah,</hi> the Jewes paid contribution, they were tributaries to the Romans.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> that Prophecy, <hi>Micah</hi> 5.2. pointing out the place of his Nativity, <hi>he was borne in Bethleem of Judea,</hi> which was the place aſſigned for Chriſts Birth, as theſe very chief Prieſts or their Predeceſſours told King <hi>Herod.</hi> But if neither the time nor place of his Birth, yet his Miracles might perfectly aſſure them that he was the <hi>Meſſiah.</hi> And therefore when Saint <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> ſent two of his Diſciples to aske him, <hi>if he were Chriſt?</hi> all the anſwer he would returne by them was this, <hi>Go, and ſhew John again thoſe things ye doe heare and ſee, the blind receive their ſight, the deafe hear, the lame walk, the lepers are cleanſed, the dead are raiſed up, &amp;c. Mat.</hi> 11.4, 5. And when Chriſt commeth, ſome asked the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>Shall he doe more Miracles then theſe which this man doth? Joh.</hi> 7.31. Though the chief Prieſts then would not believe his words, yet <hi>they might have believed him for his works ſake.</hi> But neither of theſe would prevaile with them, they had eares, yet would not heare, they had eyes, yet would not ſee. Which was a moſt notorious aggravation of their treaſon, for had they been ſtark blind, their ſin haply might have been remitted, but becauſe ſeeing they would not ſee, therefore their ſin remaineth. And this ſin of theirs ſeemeth to be no better then the very ſin againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> for againſt conſcience, out of meer malice they conſpired to put this Heire to death. And I pray God the Ring-leaders of our rebellious Reformation be not guilty of the ſelf-ſame ſin; for it ſeemeth to be out of a deſperate, inveterate malice, that notwithſtanding the preſent Treaty, ſome of them perſiſt in their conſpiracy againſt the beſt of Kings. But theſe Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers ſhall bring up the rear of my diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>I paſſe therefore from the ſecond part of the Text, the <hi>Perſon</hi> that the chief Prieſts conſpired againſt, which was the <hi>Heire,</hi> to the third, which is the manner of their conſpiracy, <hi>They reaſoned
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116082:6"/>among themſelves, ſaying, come, let us kill him.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>they reaſoned,</hi> they argued the caſe. Treaſon is a ſin of deliberation, a ſtudied ſin. All ſins are not <hi>cognita,</hi> known ſins, there are ſins of ignorance, as well as ſins of knowledge. But there is neither <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantia facti,</hi> nor <hi>ignorantia juris</hi> in treaſon, it is wilfully contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and complotted, it is a premeditated ſin. And herein ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth the hainouſneſſe of it above other ſins. To ſin out of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity or ignorance, to be <hi>overtaken in a fault,</hi> this is but (as it were) <hi>chance medley,</hi> pardonable by the law of God and men. But to ſin with a full career, of ſet purpoſe, to conſult about it, this is no leſſe then <hi>wilfull murder,</hi> a ſin that never muſt go unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned; and yet this was the ſin of theſe chief Prieſts in our Text, <hi>they reaſoned among themſelves, ſaying, come, let us kill him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Come.</hi> Wicked men uſe to call and invite one another to commit ſin, they are a ſociable ſort of people, that are unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to go to Hell alone, they entiſe and engage as many as they can to be partakers with them, they are in <hi>league and covenant,</hi> there is a combination among them, eſpecially among Traytours, ſuch as theſe chief Prieſts were, who conſpired againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> juſt as <hi>Joſeph's</hi> Brethren againſt him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>come, let us kill him. Joſeph</hi> indeed ſcaped with life, thanks to his eldeſt Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but <hi>Jeſus</hi> had not one <hi>Reuben</hi> to ſpeak for him, none but a Woman, and ſhe could not prevaile, <hi>the Kings of the earth ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding up, and the Rulers taking counſell together againſt the Lord, and againſt his Chriſt, for againſt the holy Child</hi> Jeſus <hi>both</hi> Herod <hi>and</hi> Pontius Pilate, <hi>with the Gentiles, and the people of the Jewes were gathered together, they gathered them together againſt the ſoule of the righteous, that they might condemn the innocent bloud, they reaſoned among themſelves, ſaying, come, let us kill him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Kill him.</hi> As the Devil is a murtherer, ſo all thoſe that are of his party thirſt after bloud. <hi>Shimei</hi> did a great deal of wrong to <hi>David</hi> in calling him ſo, but otherwiſe <hi>Bloudy man,</hi> and <hi>man of Belial</hi> may well go together, for there is no man deſperately wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, but he is a bloud-thirſty man. It hath been thus from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world, and will be ſo to the end. <hi>Caine was of that wicked one,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>and ſlew his Brother,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.12. This was likewiſe the reſolution of wicked <hi>Eſau, the daies of mourning for my Father are at hand, then</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>will I ſlay my Brother Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116082:7"/>Gen.</hi> 27.41. Thus <hi>Pharaoh</hi> commanded the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives to murder every Male child of the <hi>Hebrews, if it be a Son, then ye ſhall kill him, Exod.</hi> 1.16. And <hi>thus Herod ſlew all the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in Bethleem, from two years old and under, Mat.</hi> 2.16. This we read of <hi>Herodias,</hi> that nothing would ſatiate her malice but Saint <hi>John Baptiſts bloud, Mat.</hi> 14.8. Thus the <hi>Jewes</hi> cried out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Saint <hi>Paul, Away with ſuch a fellow from the earth, for it is not fit that he ſhould live, Act.</hi> 22.22. And <hi>Act.</hi> 23.12. we find ſome that <hi>bound themſelves under a curſe</hi> (they took the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi>) <hi>ſaying, that they would neither eate nor drinke, till they had killed Paul.</hi> And the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>drunk with the bloud of Saints, and with the bloud of the Martyrs of Jeſus, Rev.</hi> 17.6. I might be infinite in examples, but this in our Text ſhall be <hi>inſtar omnium,</hi> we may fee the bloudy mindedneſſe of wicked men by theſe chief Prieſts, who conſpired not to baniſh or impriſon, but even to murder Gods owne Son, <hi>they reaſoned among themſelves, ſaying, come, let us kill him. And the voices of the multitude, and of theſe chief Prieſts prevailed,</hi> this treaſon ſtood not alway in conſultation, but went on to action, what the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon counſell determined wickedly, the common people executed greedily, <hi>they caſt the Heire out of the Vineyard, and ſlew him</hi> with this dreadfull imprecation, <hi>his bloud be on us, and on our children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſeeing our Maſter was thus uſed, we muſt expect no better meaſure, but even <hi>to be killed all the day long,</hi> as the <hi>Pſalmist</hi> ſpeaketh, and <hi>to be counted as Sheep appointed to be ſlaine.</hi> The <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha,</hi> and the <hi>Omega</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> is writ in bloud,
<q>
                  <l>Sanguine fundata eſt Eccleſia, ſanguine crevit,</l>
                  <l>Sanguine firmatur, ſanguine finis erit.</l>
               </q> And we need not wonder at this, if we believe our <hi>Saviour,</hi> for it is but that which he told us long agoe, that we ſhould be hated and hunted after for his ſake, <hi>yea the time will come</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>that whoſoever killeth you will think he doth God ſervice.</hi> A Prophecy that ſeemeth to point directly at our very daies, when the blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt of Souldiers think themſelves the beſt of Saints, when mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of loyall <hi>Chriſtians</hi> goeth for pure Religion. But though <hi>our bloud be ſhed like water on every ſide,</hi> yet our God that is <hi>true and holy,</hi> will (in his good time) <hi>judge and avenge our bloud on them that dwell on the earth,</hi> there will one day be a ſtrict <hi>inquiſition
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116082:7"/>made for bloud,</hi> for the blood of <hi>Strafford</hi> and <hi>Canterbury,</hi> for the bloud of <hi>Lucas</hi> and <hi>Liſle,</hi> for the bloud of <hi>Tomkins</hi> and <hi>Chaloner,</hi> for the bloud of <hi>Yeomans, Bourchier,</hi> and <hi>Burleigh,</hi> for the bloud of <hi>Dunkin,</hi> and others in <hi>Kent,</hi> there will be a day, I ſay, if not in this, yet in the next world, when <hi>all the righteous bloud that hath</hi> of late years <hi>been ſhed</hi> in this Kingdome, ſhall be required at the hands of this tyrannicall <hi>ſatanicall</hi> generation.</p>
            <p>And ſo I paſſe from the third part of the Text, which was the <hi>manner</hi> of the <hi>chief Priests</hi> conſpiracy, <hi>they reaſoned among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſaying, come, let us kill him,</hi> to the fourth and laſt, the <hi>end</hi> of their conſpiracy, which was, that they might be Lords of the Mannour, <hi>that the inheritance may be ours, But when the Huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſaw him, they reaſoned among themſelves, ſaying, this is the Heire, come, let us kill him, that the inheritance may be ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In every action, there is both <hi>Opus,</hi> and <hi>Intentio operantis,</hi> the doing of the work, and the end for which we doe it, and by an <hi>Hyſteron proteron</hi> the laſt of theſe is firſt, what is laſt in execution, the ſame is firſt in our intention, the <hi>end</hi> being alway the <hi>beginning</hi> of the action. Now it is an axiome in <hi>Philoſophy, Finis &amp; Bonum convertuntur,</hi> let the action be what it will, <hi>Good</hi> is alway pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded for the end, either <hi>Honeſtum,</hi> or <hi>Jucundum,</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile,</hi> either an honeſt, or a pleaſant, or a profitable end, <hi>they that doe evill</hi> will ſay they doe this, <hi>that good may come of it,</hi> good to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at leaſt, though hurt to others; or if it be not good indeed, yet it ſhall ſeemingly be good; and the laſt of thoſe three ends the <hi>chief Prieſts</hi> here propound unto themſelves, <hi>Bonum utile,</hi> they ſet up profit for their end, <hi>Come, let us kill him, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance may be ours.</hi> They propound the ſame end with thoſe ſinners that <hi>Solomon</hi> cautioneth us to take heed of, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.11, 13. where hope of gaine is uſed as a motive to invite others to joyne with them, <hi>Come, let us lay wait for bloud, let us lurk privily for the innocent without cauſe, we ſhall find all pretious ſubſtance, we ſhall fill our houſes with ſpoile.</hi> And at the 19 Verſe there is juſt ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſage, <hi>So are the waies of every one that is greedy of gaine, which taketh away the life of the owners thereof.</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>—quid non mortalia pectora cogis</l>
                  <l>Auri ſacra fames?</l>
               </q> There is no villany but will go down with men, if it have a golden
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116082:8"/>bait. <hi>The love of money is the root of all evill,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Balaam</hi> will endeavour to <hi>curſe Iſrael,</hi> if he may gain but the <hi>rewards of Divination. Achan</hi> will take of the <hi>accurſed thing,</hi> if he may gain a <hi>Babyloniſh garment, two hundred ſhekels of ſilver, and a wedge of gold; Saul</hi> will ſpare the ſpoile of <hi>Amaleck,</hi> if he may gain good ſtore of <hi>rich plunder; Gehazi</hi> will tell an arrant lie to <hi>Naaman,</hi> if he may gain <hi>two talents,</hi> and <hi>new clothes; Judas</hi> will betray his own <hi>Master,</hi> if he may gain <hi>thirty pieces of ſilver;</hi> the Souldiers will ſay that <hi>Chriſt was ſtollen out of the grave,</hi> if the <hi>chief Prieſts</hi> will give them <hi>large money; Jezebel</hi> will plot <hi>Naboth's death,</hi> if ſhe may gain his <hi>Vineyard;</hi> ſhe proclaimed a <hi>faſt,</hi> yet knew no other godlineſſe but <hi>gaine:</hi> and this, this likewiſe ſet the <hi>chief Prieſts</hi> a work to conſpire the death of <hi>Chriſt, Come</hi> (ſay they) <hi>let us kill him, that the inheritance may be ours.</hi> That we may be no longer <hi>dreſſers,</hi> but <hi>poſſeſſers</hi> of the <hi>Vineyard,</hi> that there may be no Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, no Lord over us, but that the <hi>Church</hi> may be ruled and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned as we liſt, that the <hi>doctrine</hi> and <hi>diſcipline</hi> of it may be what we ſee good; nay, that we may have dominion as well over mens <hi>free-hold,</hi> as their <hi>faith,</hi> that their conſciences and coffers may both be at our command. This was the end that the <hi>chief Prieſts</hi> aimed at, when they conſpired againſt the <hi>Heire, Come, let us kill him, that the inheritance may be ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And herein the <hi>Biſhop of Rome</hi> looketh very like them, who ſtileth himſelf <hi>Chriſts Vicar,</hi> S. <hi>Peters Succeſſour,</hi> he ſaith, that he is the <hi>right heire,</hi> the head of <hi>Chriſts</hi> whole <hi>Church,</hi> he arrogateth the title of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall Biſhop,</hi> he challengeth (as it were) the <hi>Wardſhip,</hi> nay, the <hi>Lordſhip</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> whatſoever he ſaith muſt go for <hi>Goſpel,</hi> meerly becauſe he ſaith it, he taketh upon him more then <hi>Apoſtolicall</hi> authority, even that which is <hi>Gods</hi> pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar, <hi>To forgive ſins,</hi> for which cauſe fall the ſilly people unto him, and thereout he ſucketh no ſmall advantage, it is a maſſe of money that his <hi>Pardons</hi> annually bring in to him. And other ſtratagems he hath, but all to enrich himſelfe. He will releaſe men out of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> if they will give him money enough, he will warrant they ſhal be <hi>heires of Heaven</hi> though herein he contradict himſelf, for ſometimes he telleth them, <hi>that they can never be ſure of Heaven till they come thither,</hi> yet thus he befooleth the people, <hi>he will war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant them an inheritance in Heaven,</hi> if they will make him their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116082:8"/>Heire on earth. His whole Religion indeed is nothing elſe but a politick project to get money, he feedeth not the flock of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but feedeth upon it, he keepeth the people in ignorance, ſeeking not <hi>them,</hi> but <hi>theirs, He,</hi> and all his <hi>Cardinals, Monks,</hi> and <hi>Abbots,</hi> they ſeek their own profit and preferment, their own gain and greatneſſe, like theſe <hi>chief Priests</hi> in our Text, whoſe aime was to get the inheritance, <hi>Come,</hi> (ſay they) <hi>let us kill him that the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance may be ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I have gone thorow the ſeverall parts of the <hi>Text.</hi> A few words of application, and I have done.</p>
            <p>Our Text is a plain conſpiracy againſt our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and the conſpiracy of <hi>Levellers</hi> againſt our <hi>Soveraigne</hi> wil match it right. Our <hi>Saviour</hi> let out his <hi>Vineyard</hi> to <hi>Huſbandmen,</hi> ſo our <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne</hi> did (as it were) let out His Kingdome to <hi>States-men,</hi> he gave them power to prune and dreſſe it, to take off ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to rectifie enormities, he gave them their hearts deſire, and denied them not the requeſt of their lips, he granted that which none but a moſt indulgent <hi>Land-lord</hi> would ere have granted, they asked a leaſe of him, and he gave them a long leaſe, longer then any of their Predeceſſours ever had, he made them no Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants for years, much leſſe at will, but reſerving his fee-ſimple, I mean his Negative voice, he gave it under his hand, that he would not re-enter, till they themſelves conſented to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O fortunatos nimium, bona ſi ſua norint, Agricolas!</hi> What men were ever ſo happy, as theſe might have been? How might the glory of their <hi>God,</hi> of their <hi>King,</hi> of their <hi>Countrey,</hi> and even of <hi>themſelves</hi> have been advanced by them? But neglecting the <hi>three firſt,</hi> they aimed chiefly at the <hi>laſt,</hi> at their owne glory. For aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoone as their unlucky leaſe was ſealed, they ſtraight way thought themſelves free-holders, taking <hi>Regall</hi> power upon them, as if the <hi>Militia,</hi> the <hi>King's inheritance</hi> had been theirs, they deveſted their <hi>Soveraigne</hi> of it, and inveſted themſelves with it, making the <hi>Heire</hi> of <hi>three Kingdomes</hi> (though <hi>no Child</hi> in any thing, <hi>but malice</hi>) <hi>to differ nothing from a ſervant, when he was Lord of all,</hi> for, without him, they took upon them to un-make, and to make Lawes, ſaying, we have the legiſlative power, <hi>who is Lord over us?</hi> And that they might the better enjoy the <hi>Crowne,</hi> they entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Covenant</hi> againſt the <hi>Miter,</hi> reſolved to aboliſh the excellent
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116082:9"/>government of <hi>Biſhops, root and branch.</hi> And becauſe the <hi>King,</hi> both againſt his <hi>oath</hi> and <hi>conſcience</hi> would not yeild to this, Come, ſaid they, let us compell him to it by force of Armes; they ſet the people awork firſt to mutiny, then to fight againſt him, as who ſhould ſay, <hi>we have no part in</hi> Charles, <hi>neither have we inheritance in the Son of</hi> James, <hi>every man to his tents, ô</hi> England, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed open War againſt Him and His Adherents, giving out Commiſſions to <hi>kill and ſlay</hi> all perſons that ſhould oppoſe them, their <hi>Soveraigne</hi> Lord the King was not excepted, for bullets can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſtinguiſh between a <hi>Scepter</hi> and a <hi>ſhovel, the ſword</hi> (as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſaid) <hi>devoureth one as well as another.</hi> But ſeeing they could not kill Him in the <hi>field,</hi> they have ſince attempted it in the <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> it is too apparent that the Ring-leaders of this Rebellion had an hand in that late Conſpiracy againſt Him. Nor is it only <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolus,</hi> but even <hi>Rex</hi> that they ſtrike at, going about not onely to kill the Perſon, but the very office of King, I ſpeak of the level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Faction, all this while, Come, ſay they, let us break his bonds aſunder, and caſt away his cords from us; come, let us make no more addreſſes to him, but let us make our ſelves a free-State, that the name of Monarch may be no more in remembrance. And to effect this, they have made the Kingdome not only a field, but even a ſea of bloud, breathing out nothing but ſlaughter againſt all loyall Subjects, killing and ſlaying, butchering and murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their Brethren, <hi>whoſe bloud they have ſhed like Water on every ſide,</hi> like that Woman in the <hi>Revelation, drinking themſelves drunk with the bloud of Saints,</hi> and with the bloud of the Martyrs of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> in which noble Army thoſe matchleſſe Knights murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at <hi>Colcheſter</hi> may well be liſted.</p>
            <p>It is no mervaile if theſe bloud-hounds will not have <hi>Gods Commandements</hi> read in Churches, for one of theſe telleth them expreſly, they muſt <hi>doe no murder,</hi> and as almoſt all the reſt, ſo moſt eſpecially that ſixt Commandement they count Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phall, for <hi>murdering of men</hi> is their profeſſion, and a great part of their Religion, as if <hi>Mars</hi> were their <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Mahomet</hi> their <hi>Meſſiah.</hi> Let them uſurp the name of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> while they will, I am ſure their bloudy practices proclaime them arrant <hi>Turkes. Chriſtianity,</hi> is for the <hi>ſaving of mens lives; Turciſme,</hi> for the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of them,</hi> and ſuch is the Religion of theſe <hi>Levellers, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116082:9"/>is in their way,</hi> they are ſtill oppoſing of Treaties, <hi>the way of peace have they not known,</hi> like horſe-leaches, they never think they have <hi>bloud enough,</hi> they would have it even unto the horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridles, as if they had a mind to ſwim in bloud.</p>
            <p>And all this under pretence of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Reformation,</hi> a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ſo pitiful &amp; ſo thread bare, that I wonder men are not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be ſeduced by it, for Religion was ever made the ſtalking-horſe to Rebellion, and indeed this muſt be the pretence, or elſe the deſigne will ſoon be daſht, for ſhould they proclaime them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves open Atheiſts, and profeſſe the ſubverting of Religion, I think the world is not ſo bad, but that it would tear them all in pieces. They are bound therefore to pretend <hi>piety,</hi> like <hi>Abſolom</hi> and <hi>Jezebel,</hi> but their actions tell the world that they ayme at other ends, even at <hi>Libertiniſme,</hi> that they may be lawleſſe, that they may doe what they liſt, that they may roare and whore, yet never be queſtioned or controuled; for there are no men living more given to the fleſh, then they that pretend ſo extreamly to the ſpirit; but chiefly, the Inheritance, the Kingdomes wealth is that they ayme at, they ſeek not the kingdom of God, but the riches of this Kingdome, that the revenue of the Crowne, and the patrimony of the Miter, and the Eſtate of every loyall Subject may be theirs. Moſt truly may that of the Prophet be applied to them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.17. <hi>their eyes, and their hearts are not but for their covetouſneſſe, and for to ſhed innocent bloud, and for oppreſſion, and for violence to doe it;</hi> witneſſe their <hi>Sequeſtrations,</hi> their <hi>Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> their <hi>Exciſe,</hi> their <hi>Fift,</hi> and <hi>Twentieth part;</hi> beſides their greedines in getting all the gainful Offices of the Kingdom. Their <hi>love of money</hi> hath been <hi>the root of all our evils,</hi> we may ſee this by their dividing of the ſpoile, their ſharing of the Kingdoms wealth among themſelves, eſpecially, by their ſacrilegious ſelling and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping of Church-lands; they had long agoe ended the Warre, or rather had never begun it, but to get theſe Lands: <hi>they kill,</hi> as Saint <hi>James</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>becauſe they deſire to have, to have other mens poſſeſſions,</hi> the whole world, and even their own conſciences beare witneſſe to this truth. And their Chaplaines of the Aſſembly are juſt like them, thoſe Journey-men-Rebels, that love the wages of unrighteouſneſſe, that have ſo much by the day to make Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on good by Scripture; an heart they have exerciſed with covetous
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116082:10"/>practiſes, through covetouſneſſe, with fained words, making mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe of men. Their ayme is to get the greateſt Livings, even Pluralities, which once they ſo much railed at, and under the name, forſooth, of <hi>Lecturers,</hi> they creep into Deanes and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendaries houſes, ſome get Maſterſhips of Colledges, ſome of Hoſpitals, all their ayme is that the inheritance, the profitable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments may be theirs.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not need to rake this dunghill, nor ſtir this <hi>Camerina</hi> any further. It is moſt evident how bloudy and covetous all theſe levelling Vine-dreſſers are. <hi>What therefore ſhall the Lord of the Vineyard doe unto them?</hi> Sure in juſtice he might deſtroy them (though he delighteth more in mercy) and might <hi>let out his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard to others,</hi> he might diſcard theſe unjuſt Judges, he might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place theſe unfaithfull Stewards, theſe <hi>Zimries</hi> deſerve no <hi>peace,</hi> no <hi>pardon,</hi> that would have <hi>ſlain their Maſter,</hi> theſe <hi>Shebaes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to have <hi>their heads thrown over the Wall,</hi> theſe <hi>Hamans</hi> to be <hi>executed upon their owne gallowes, thoſe mine enemies,</hi> (might the King ſay) <hi>which would not that I ſhould reigne over them, bring them hither, and ſlay them before me.</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>—neque eſt lex juſtior ulla</l>
                  <l>Quàm necis artifices arte perire ſuâ.</l>
               </q> They might juſtly be ſerved, as the Scythian Queen ſerved <hi>Cyrus,</hi> have their heads thrown into a bloud-boule, with this exprobra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their tyranny, <hi>Satiate vos ſanguine, ſanguiſugae, quem ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtis,</hi> their heads ſhould down to the grave with bloud, theirs eſpecially that have ſhed the bloud of war in peace, that for meer envy, have murdered their Captives in cold bloud. And methinks indeed theſe men of bloud ſhould have ſuch an hell within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that like <hi>Cain,</hi> they ſhould <hi>be afraid that every one which meeteth them, will ſlay them.</hi> For <hi>bloud-thirſty men,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>ſhall not live out halfe their daies,</hi> if they doe, they ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome die peaceably in their beds,
<q>
                  <l>Ad generum Ceteris ſine caede &amp; vulnere paci</l>
                  <l>Deſcendunt—&amp; ſiccâ morte tiranni.</l>
               </q> If any aske why I rip up theſe mens actions, in a time of <hi>Treaty,</hi> I Anſwer, that I have, in a manner, their owne order for it, they returned thanks to thoſe men that petitioned lately againſt the Treaty, whereby it is evident that they approved of their Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116082:10"/>and one paſſage in that Petition was to this purpoſe, that <hi>no baſe Act of Oblivion might obliterate their doings, but that there might be an Act rather for the propagating of their memoriall to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity.</hi> But to ſpeak no more of them being abſent, let me now apply my ſelf to you here preſent, and let me intreat you to be no longer <hi>partakers in their ſins, walke not ye in the way with them, refraine your feet from their path, for their feet run to evill, and make haſte to ſhed bloud,</hi> and bloud-ſhed, Brethren, how light ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever now eſteemed, is a moſt crying ſin, the cries of it enter into the eares of the Lord of Sabbath. <hi>Waſh</hi> therefore not your <hi>hands</hi> onely, but your <hi>hearts</hi> too from this ſin, let no bloudy thoughts any longer lodge in you. As the death of men is dear in the ſight of God, ſo let it be in your ſight. Remember what Almighty God ſaith, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.5, 6. <hi>Surely your bloud of your lives will I require, at the hand of every mans Brother will I require the life of man. Who ſo ſheddeth mans bloud, by man ſhall his bloud be ſhed.</hi> Take heed then of ſhaking hands with thoſe men that delight in bloud, this ſin will not ſuffer God to be quiet, till he avenge it. To the ſlaine, his eares are open, but faſt ſhut to thoſe that ſlay them, all your daies of Faſting and Humiliation will be ineffectuall if ye be againſt <hi>the Treaty,</hi> if ye be ſtill for War, though ye make never ſo many Prayers, God will not hear you, ſo long as your hands are full of bloud. <hi>Waſh</hi> your ſelves therefore I beſeech you, <hi>make you cleane</hi> from the bloud of all men, be no longer acceſſary to murder, by raiſing Money to maintaine War, ye know that <hi>no murderer</hi> (no not a ſecond-hand murderer) <hi>hath eternal life abiding in him.</hi> Let then your prayer be, that God would deliver you from this kind of bloud-guiltineſſe, and hereafter make better uſe of your money, make it not the price of bloud. <hi>Curſed be he,</hi> ſaith God by <hi>Jeremy, that keepeth back his ſword from bloud, Jer.</hi> 48.10. A place that Aſſembly-men have ſtrangely wreſted of late yeares, preſſing it upon mens conſciences as a warrant for them to cut throats, urging it as a Commiſſion and command for them to <hi>kill and ſlay;</hi> and many thouſands have followed their pernitious doctrine, even LONDON, the ſometime <hi>faithfull City is become an Harlot, righteouſneſſe</hi> did once lodge in it, but now <hi>murderers.</hi> But let not theſe bloudy wolviſh Prophets ſeduce you any more. <hi>Wo to the bloudy City, this is the voice of the Lords
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116082:11"/>Prophets, and if any man teach you otherwiſe, let him be accurſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>O that ye would know therefore in this your day the things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto your peace, leſt otherwiſe they be hid for ever from your eyes.</hi> Conſider what God ſaith to the Jewes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.19, 20. for the very ſame he ſaith now to you, <hi>If ye be willing and obedient,</hi> willing to have your King reſtored, and will henceforth be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to him, <hi>ye ſhall eate the good of the land, but</hi> if ye refuſe <hi>his gratious pardon, and reſolve ſtill to rebel againſt him, ye ſhal be devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the ſword; for the mouth of the Lord bath ſpoken it.</hi> If ye ſtill keep <hi>up the ſword,</hi> ye will, in the end, <hi>periſh by it,</hi> your ſword will certainly penetrate your own heart. <hi>Obey not them therefore that think they can kill the body,</hi> and that would have you make a trade of killing, but <hi>obey him that can kill body and ſoule,</hi> whoſe expreſſe command is, that <hi>ye ſhall not kill. If ye will not follow peace, ye ſhall never ſee the Lord.</hi> If here ye baniſh that from you. He will here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after baniſh you from him he will renounce you with thoſe words of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 139.19. <hi>Depart from me, ye bloudy, ye bloud-thirſty men.</hi> And as God abhorreth the <hi>bloudy, Pſal.</hi> 5. ſo doth he the <hi>covetous man, Pſal.</hi> 10. He that ſaid, <hi>Doe not kill,</hi> ſaid alſo, <hi>Doe not covet,</hi> as therefore ye muſt abſtaine from <hi>bloud,</hi> ſo muſt ye from <hi>covetouſneſſe, let not this be on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e named amongst you, as becommeth Saints,</hi> but learn of the Apoſtle <hi>in whatſoever ſtate ye are, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to be content;</hi> ſee that ye covet no mans <hi>ſilver,</hi> or <hi>gold,</hi> or <hi>apparell,</hi> but <hi>having food and rayment, be therewith content.</hi> Ye know whoſe law it is, <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet thy neighbours houſe;</hi> take heed then, Brethren, of coveting Biſhops houſes, or any thing elſe that is anothers, and not yours. <hi>All covet, all loſe,</hi> ye may have good Scripture for it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.10. <hi>I will give their Wives unto others, and their fields to them that ſhall inherit them: for every one from the leaſt even unto the greateſt is given to covetouſneſſe, from the Prophet, even unto the Prieſt.</hi> They that greedly get away other mens, beget a gangrene in their owne eſtates.
<q>De male quaeſitis vix gaudet tertius hares.</q> 
               <hi>Take heed therefore,</hi> as our Saviour exhorteth, <hi>and beware of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe.</hi> Conſider what S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.5. <hi>no covetous man, who is an idolater, hath any inheritance in the Kingdome of Chriſt, and of God;</hi> and conſider what the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9. <hi>They that will be rich</hi> (as it were, whether God will or no) <hi>fall
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116082:11"/>into temptation, and a ſnare, and into many fooliſh and hurtfull luſts, which drown men in deſtruction and perdition.</hi> Covetouſneſſe temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth men to murder, this is that maketh Levellers ſo bloudy as they are: <hi>from whence come wars and fightings among you?</hi> Surely <hi>covetouſneſſe</hi> hath been the originall of them all, the lower ſort of people ſtrive to be in an higher roome, the poore would faine turn tables with the rich, they would thus have <hi>every valley to be filled,</hi> and <hi>every mountain and hill to be laid low,</hi> as if, in this ſenſe, every man were bound to ſeek anothers wealth, they that were borne to nothing, ſtrive to get others birth rights, calling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, for ſooth, <hi>the Saints,</hi> who, they ſay, muſt <hi>inherit the earth;</hi> they would make themſelves rich, that have nothing, and others poore, that have great riches.</p>
            <p>But to conclude this, Brethren, is not the office of Saints, it is Gods office, <hi>it is the Lord that maketh poore, and maketh rich.</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume not then to take Gods office out of his hand, ſtrive not to make your ſelves rich, if God have made you poore, but be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with that portion of outward things that he hath given you; <hi>the ſilver is mine, and the Gold is mine, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, Hag.</hi> 2.8. Deny him not therefore that priviledge, which your owne ſelves challenge, give him leave to doe <hi>what he pleaſeth with his owne; let not the leaſt root of covetouſneſſe remaine in you,</hi> remember that <hi>godlineſſe with contentment is great gaine, if the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of others increaſe, ſet not your hearts upon them, ſeek not theſe things below, but thoſe above, ſtrive not for an inheritance on earth, but to have one in heaven; that ye may baniſh cruelty, let covetouſneſs be baniſhed firſt,</hi> that ye may not thirſt after other mens blouds, covet not their goods, <hi>baſt thou killed,</hi> ſaith God to <hi>Ahab, and alſo taken poſſeſſion?</hi> well, ye know what became of him &amp; <hi>Jezebel</hi> for this; ſtifle therefore not onely you murtherous, but alſo your covetous thoughts, if ye muſt needs be killing, <hi>mortifie your earthly members,</hi> if ye muſt needs be coveting, <hi>covet earneſtly the beſt gifts;</hi> God hath choſen the poor of this world, rich in faith, to be heires of his kingdome; labour therefore to get the gold of faith, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ye may be rich towards God, and then although here ye have no temporall inheritance, yet hereafter ye ſhall have one far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ye ſhall be heires apparent unto Heaven, ye ſhall inherit glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, God will give you an inheritance among all them which are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116082:12"/>ſanctified, though now ye are in your nonage, yet at the laſt day ye ſhall be perfect men, ye ſhall be of full age, ye ſhall attain to the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt, who ſhall then invite you to enter upon your inheritance in theſe words, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of the world.</hi> Which God of his infinite mercy vouchſafe to grant unto us all, for the merits of his beloved Son, our bleſſed Saviour. To whom, with the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, Three Perſons, one Immortall, Inviſible, Indiviſible, only wiſe God, be rendred and aſcribed, as moſt due is, All Honour, Glory, Power, Praiſe, Might, Majeſty, Wiſdome, and Dominion, the reſidue of this bleſſed day preſent, and for evermore world without end, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
